PROFESSOR: So the planning agent comes
up with a better plan, but of course
it's a complex planning problem.
And in general, we're going to have to
be able to formulate what we mean by a
planning problem.
Or the problems themselves, we
call them search problems.
So what is a search problem?
Well, a search problem can be
for something like get me
to the closest dot.
Get me to any dot.
Eat all the dots in as short
a time as possible.
These are the kinds of problems we
want to be able to formulate.
So what are they formally?
Well, you need a state space.
The state space is essentially in codes
how the world is at a certain
point along the progression
of your plan.
It is an abstraction of the world.
We'll come back to this.
So for the case of eating all of the
dots, your state space might be a
position for Pac-Man, and the collection
of dots which remain
encoded in some way.
So that's your state space.
You then need a successor function.
The successor function in some sense
models how you think the world works.
It tells you, all right, from this state
here, if I go north, I'll end up
in a state where the Pac-Man position
has moved one north, and one of the
dots has been eaten.
OK, in particular, that
dot has been eaten.
If I go east, I'll get
some other position.
OK, the successor function takes a state
in the state space, and then
what it does is it tells you where you
can get to immediately, what actions
achieve that, and how much they cost
in the case you have cost.
If you don't have cost, maybe
all the costs are one.
So the states space models how the
world is, the successor function
models how it evolves in response
to your actions.
You need a start state, which is right
now I'm in the lower left hand corner.
The start state model is where you
begin, and you need a goal test.
The goal test looks at a sate and
tells you whether or not you've
achieved your goals.
So if you're trying to eat all of the
dots, the goals might be something
like all dots are gone.
But maybe you don't actually
care where Pac-Man is.
Or maybe you're like a type a Pac-Man,
and you want to eat all the dots and
end up in the middle, right?
Well, now your goal state has
to mention Pac-Man as well.
OK, that's the search problem.
State space successor function,
start state and goal test.
What is a solution to such a problem?
A solution is a sequence of actions.
We can call it a plan.
A sequence of actions which transforms
the start state into a state that
passes the goal test.
So it might be from the start state,
your solution is north, north, east,
south, south, and so on.
All right.
Remember, this is very important.
This will come up over and
over in this course.
Search problems are just models.
So you've got the real world,
that's complicated.
You've got your agent.
And your agent has some kind of very
rough model of the world that's used
for this problem.
And always remember that your search
is only going to be good, and only
correct if your model is appropriate
for the search problem.
You don't want to abstract too much,
because if you abstract too much, then
you can't actually solve your problem.
We'll see examples of that.
And if you abstract too little, you
end up dealing with all the
complexities of the world,
and that's bad news.
Search problems are always models.
Here's an example.
Let's say I'm traveling in Romania.
And let's say I'm at the city of Arad,
and I'm trying to get to the airport
at Bucharest, OK?
I have in front of me a map.
And map is a good example of
an abstraction of how the
world actually is.
The real world has actual roads with
actual cars on them, some of them
happened to be closed.
There's some speed bumps.
There's birds flying overhead.
Any number of things going
on in the real world.
In your abstraction, they're simply
cities connected by roads with say,
mileage or times connecting them.
So here's a model, if I want to get from
Arad to Bucharest, what does my
search probably need to include?
Well, it probably doesn't need to
include the birds overhead.
They're probably not relevant.
But what does it need to have?
Well, there's a little bit
of an art to this.
You're going to do a bunch of examples,
working through on your own,
how to formulate a search problem, but
let's talk through some together.
So what are the states need to be?
Minimally, my state space needs to
support a goal test, and in the goal
I'm at Bucharest.
So I need to be able to look at my
state, figure out whether or not I'm
at Bucharest.
So minimally, the state space
needs to be a set of cities.
We'll see whether that's enough.
We need a successor function, which
is what are the things I can do?
Well, my actions are to take roads.
So the successor function has, from
any given city, I can go to some
adjacent city, and here there's a
natural cost function, which is for
example the distance.
So from Arad I have three actions.
I have the go to Zerind action, the go
to Sibiu action, and the go to the
Timisoara action.
And where's my start state?
In this case, Arad.
What's my goal test?
Is the state equal to Bucharest?
So in this case, the goal test is really
just a goal state, but in many
cases it's a test.
So what does the solution look like?
Well, it some sequence of roads.
So what goes into a state space?
How did I know that it was cities and
not pairs of cities and not cities
plus birds or whatever?
Well, an important distinction that
we've been alluding to so far is this
notion of world state versus
search or model state.
So the world state includes every
last detail of the environment.
In Pac-Man, it's got where you are,
where the dots are, where the power
pellets are, ghosts, walls, score,
whatever you could possibly have in
the world, that's the
entire world state.
In general, you don't want to plan
over that because that's
a very large set.
The search state keeps only the
details needed for planning.
So it's an abstraction, and the amount
of abstraction your safe getting away
with depends on the problem
you're solving.
So for example, if I just want to pass,
I'd like to get my agent from
one x,y coordinate to another,
it's actually a lot
like getting to Bucharest.
Then well, you're states could just
be the x,y location, right?
I can check at the goal, am
I at the right location?
And these states are enough to take my
actions North, South, East and West
and evolve the relevant
parts of the world.
So for example, if I go East for this
problem, it doesn't matter whether I
eat a dot, and so I can just
change my x, y coordinate.
So in this case, the successor function
updates your location only,
and so again, we can see that
the state just being an x,y
pair is good enough.
The goal test is, are we
at the goal position?
So that pathing.
We'll actually talk more
about pathing later.
It's a very common search problem
that you'll see a lot.
Let's say however, my problem is the
much more difficult problem that
mastermind Pac-Man might solve,
and that is the problem
of eat all the dots.
Well, now your states can't
just be an x,y coordinate.
Because, for example, you can't
run your goal test.
If I tell you, hey, I figured out
a plan to get to 4,7, did
I eat all the dots?
You'll say, I don't know,
tell me about the dots.
So if you're going to eat all the dots,
probably the dots need to make
it into the formulation.
So in particular, one thing that will
work for this problem is if your
states in the state space are a pair
where on one hand you've got your
position, the x,y coordinate, and on
the other pair you've got some
encoding of what dots are left like say,
a boolean for each dot whether
it's been eaten or not.
Your actions are the same, but now the
successor function updates your
location and also the set of dots.
What's your goal test now?
Your goal test is going to
be something like, are
all the dots false?
What about my position?
It's not relevant to the goal.
Well, why do I even have it?
Well, you can't actually use your
successor function properly and figure
out whether you've just eaten a dot
unless you know where you are.
So the requirements on the state space
partly come from the ability to run
the goal test, they partly come from
the ability to find the correct
successor function, and you'll have a
lot of practice formulating these
kinds of problems.
Lets talk quickly about
state space sizes.
Why don't I just search
over the world state?
Well, here it is.
So here's a grid.
It's kind of a weird grid.
There aren't dots on every position.
But on this grid, there are
120 agent positions.
OK, places where we could
stick the Pac-Man.
There are 30 food dots.
There are 12 positions the
ghosts could be in.
And the agent could be facing
north, south, east, or west.
That matters for, say, the graphics.
OK.
So that's the full world state.
Let's think about how many of
various things there are.
Well, how many world states are there?
Well lets think.
The world state has to encode
the agent positions.
That's 120.
And then, it has to encode which
direction the agents facing.
So that's four.
That's not super interesting.
And we've got two ghosts.
One ghost could be in
any of 12 positions.
And so could the other ghost.
So, 12 squared.
And then, kind of the killer here, is
the world state encode the exact
configuration of which dots
are present or absent.
So what's that?
That is 2 to the 30th.
OK.
That's bad.
So this is a lot of world states.
We would rather not have any procedure
which enumerates these or even
threatens that it might
enumerate them.
OK?
So, lots of world states.
That's why we don't plan
over world states.
However, how many states are
there required for pathing?
Well, it's just the Pac-Man position.
So how many?
Just the 120.
Much, much better.
That's why we abstract.
How about the states for
eat all the dots?
It had a position 120.
Doesn't care about the ghosts, doesn't
care about the facing, but it does
care about the dot configuration.
So, it's actually pretty big.
Turns out, almost any search problem you
could possibly care about in the
real world has some huge exponential
search space.
So in general, always remember that.
The search space is so large that you
will never be able to a enumerate it.
And all we're going to be talking about
is algorithms that, hopefully,
find you a solution, while avoiding
enumerating the entire search space.
And in general, we'd like to the
enumerate as little of it as possible.